Anthony Garland Adair papers, Inclusive: 1929-1966, undated; Bulk: undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Anthony Garland Adair papers
Inclusive: 1929-1966, undated; Bulk: undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
506
Adair, A. Garland (Anthony Garland), 1889 - 1966
3 document boxes
The Anthony Garland Adair papers contains correspondence, literary productions, and other related materials regarding the Texas Memorial Museum, which Adair was instrumental in founding and later worked as curator of history.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Anthony Garland Adair was born in Queen City, Texas on 1889 March 28, the son of J.B. And Mattie (Palmer) Adair. He attended Wesley College in Terrell, Texas and the University of Texas, then entered the army in 1917. On 1918 September 1 he was commissioned as a second lieutenant. A few weeks later, on 1918 September 22, Adair married Gladys Marie Ingram, a schoolteacher from Texarkana. Together, the couple had three children: two daughters and a son.
Following World War I, Adair edited and published newspapers across the state in Hico, Mexia, Breckenridge, and McCamey. He was named a delegate to national Democratic conventions twice; in 1920 from Hico and in 1924 from Mexia. Adair became active in the American Legion and was named commander of the Fifth Division in 1930. In 1932, he moved to Austin and assumed the duties of department historian for this branch of the American Legion. He was named chairman of the Centennial Committee of the American Legion of Texas in 1935. The committee sponsored legislation to authorize the organization of a state museum. Adair came up with the idea to sell souvenir coins to raise money for this project. Fifty cent silver coins commemorating the Texas Centennial were minted by the federal government for the fundraiser and the sales of these coins garnered approximately $92,000.
Upon the opening of the Texas Memorial Museum, Adair was named curator of patriotic exhibits. Later, he became curator of history at the museum, and he held the position until his retirement in 1959. He coauthored several books about Texas, including Texas, Its History with Ellen B. Coates (1954) and Austin and Commodore Perry with E.H. Perry, Sr. (1956). He also edited a series of Texas history periodicals during the 1940s and 1950s, including Texas Pictorial Handbook and Under Texas Skies.
Anthony Adair was an honorary life member of the Sons of the Republic of Texas, as well as a life member of the Texas State Historical Association, a fellow of the Texas Academy of Science, and a member of the Texas Press Association. He was a member of the Knights of the Order of San Jacinto and executive director of the Texas Heritage Foundation. Adair died in Temple, Texas on 1966 December 14 and is buried in the State Cemetery in Austin.
Scope and Content
The Anthony Garland Adair papers consist of four series: Correspondence, Biographical Materials, Literary Productions, and Subject Files. The correspondence series has letters and telegrams to and from Anthony G. Adair. The letters and telegrams involve both personal and professional subjects. Biographical Materials is a series comprised of various collected items and articles about Adair’s life, work, and achievements at the Texas Memorial Museum.
As a curator at the Texas Memorial Museum, Adair wrote and commissioned numerous reports for the museum. The Literary Productions series contains page proofs of long manuscripts and shorter history reports about Texas. Subject Files is the most expansive series in Anthony G. Adair’s papers. The materials are diverse, ranging from maps and geographic information to Texas organization applications and publications. The information in this series focuses on the state of Texas, which fit the mission of the Texas Memorial Museum at the time.
Arrangement
The Anthony Garland Adair papers contain four series: I. Correspondence, II. Biographical Materials, III. Literary Productions, and IV. Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 506. Acquired 1970-07-20
Related Resources
Related references
Adams, Willena C. “Adair, Anthony Garland.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2019 November 9.
Find A Grave, Inc. “Anthony Garland Adair.” Memorial #7608019, citing Texas State Cemetery, Austin, Travis County, Texas, USA. Accessed 2019 November 9.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Adair, A. Garland (Anthony Garland), 1889-1966.
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas Memorial Museum -- History.
Places
Texas -- History.
Subjects
Museums -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Page proofs.; Publications.
- Correspondence, 1929-1966; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence to and from Anthony G. Adair. The series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Biographical Materials, 1944-1959; 2
  This series contains biographical information about Anthony G. Adair. The series is in good condition.
  - Biographical Materials, 1944-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Literary Productions, undated; 3
  The series consists of various transcripts and reports written or commissioned by Anthony G. Adair for the Texas Memorial Museum. The series is in good condition.
  - Heroes of the Alamo—typescripts and galley proofs, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Heroes of the Alamo, page proofs (1 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Heroes of the Alamo, page proofs (2 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Heroes of the Alamo, page proofs (3 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Keeping Tabs on Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Texas Heroes and Heroines of Education, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “Texas Facts”, “Know Texas”, “Do You Know Texas?”, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “Under Texas Skies”, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Subject Files, undated; 4
  The series contains materials produced for and about the Texas Memorial Museum. The series is in good condition.
  - American Legion, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “The Camel Corps—The Jefferson Davis’ Experiment”, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Compositions, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Dams of Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Education in Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - First National Bank of San Antonio, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Geology of Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Highway Beautification, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Holy Land, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Industries and Resources of Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Organizations, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Republic of Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Texana, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Texas Statehood Commission, Harris County, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Texas Statehood Centennial, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Texas Statehood Commission (1 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Texas Statehood Commission (2 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Texas Statehood Commission (3 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Texas Council for Economic Development, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Texas Epidemics, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Texas Heritage Foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Texas Heroes and Heroines, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Texas Memorial Museum, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Texas Revolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Texas Statesmen, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - University Centennial Exposition, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)